A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Program Files of Bernard McDonald FA607
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Program Files of Bernard McDonald
1980-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
McDonald, Bernard
Ford Foundation
FA607
1.31 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series by file type.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Bernard McDonald Files, 1980-1982
Series II. Southwest Initiative Files, 1991-1992
Biographical / Historical
The work of what became the Urban Poverty Program began when the Public Affairs Program was formally established in 1952. One of the goals of the new program was to work toward greater equality of opportunity for minority groups. In 1965, Public Affairs was succeeded by the National Affairs Division, created to focus on deep-rooted problems facing American society. Program areas under the National Affairs Division included Social Development and Urban and Metropolitan Development. In 1981, a reorganization of the Foundation replaced National Affairs with the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP).
The Urban Poverty Program was established in October 1981 as a subdivision of USIAP, taking over programs formerly administered by the divisions of National Affairs and Education and Public Policy. It administered programs benefiting the poor and inner-city residents in areas that included community development, employment and training, welfare, teen pregnancy, poverty, crime, and precollege education. It also assumed oversight of the programs in Population and of new programs to combat infant and child mortality. The Urban Poverty Program became a program area within a newly organized Program Division in 1988 and was merged into the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) in 1996.
Biographical / Historical
Bernard McDonald graduated from Hunter College in 1964 with a B.A. in Economics and received an M.A. in Secondary Education from Brooklyn College in 1968. In 1979, he joined the Ford Foundation National Affairs Division as a Program Officer in Social Development. He then served as Program Officer In Charge/Director of Urban Poverty from 1981 to1987. In 1987, he became Director of the Special Project in Community Development in the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Office of the Vice President. His work in Urban Poverty focused on supporting the efforts of poor communities to build their own economic enterprises and building the economic capacities of minority individuals through education and job training. To this end, sustaining and building the capacity of community development corporations (CDCs) committed to physical, economic, and social revitalization became a vital component of the Foundation's strategic approach to alleviating urban poverty. This was carried out through making long-term grants and Program Related Investments (PRIs) to numerous CDCs.
Mr. McDonald also served on the Ford Foundation Minority Pipeline, Rural America, and Refugee and Migrant task forces. The Minority Pipeline Task Force, later renamed the Committee to Improve the Professional Opportunities for Minorities, aimed to increase minority access to professional fields through implementing progressive affirmative action policies in the Foundation's grantmaking. Through the Task Force, the Foundation funded scholarships, internships and research opportunities for minority students and scholars. The Rural America Task Force was funded by a Delegated Authority Project (DAP) grant and was charged with improving agricultural productivity, irrigation, and opportunities for rural employment. The Refugee and Migrants Task Force focused on aiding refugees resettling in the United States, particularly from Haiti and Southeast Asia.
Mr. McDonald left the Foundation in October 1989 for a faculty position at the Pratt Institute. There, he directed the Ford Foundation-sponsored Community Development Corporation Oral History Project. He died in 1991 at age 49.
Scope and Contents
Contains Bernard McDonald files and Southwest Initiative files.
- Bernard McDonald Files, 1980-1982; I
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1980 (1 of 9) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1980 (2 of 9) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1980 (3 of 9) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports, incl. "The Intersecting Needs of Working Women and Their Young Children" (4 of 9), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Report, "Economic Foundations of Women in the Labor Market" by Barbara B. Reagan (5 of 9), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1980 (6 of 9) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1980 (7 of 9) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1980 (8 of 9) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Meeting with FAT, Norton, Height, et al (Sep 5, 1980) (9 lf 9) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1981 (1 of 4) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1981 (2 of 4) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1981 (3 of 4) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Re: WPG Meetings, Conferences, Grant Proposals, Affirmative Action, Abortion, Feminism, etc., 1981 (4 of 4) (Box 1)
  - Women's Program Group Files, 1982 (Box 1)
- Southwest Initiative Files, 1991-1992; II
  - National Demograhics -- Ford Foundation Reports, Reference Re: U.S. Hispanic Population, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Southwest General Description -- Southwest (all) Demographics and Poverty, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Southwest General Description -- Fertility, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Southwest General Description -- Household Income, 1992 (Box 1)